Guide to the Paul A. Samuelson papers, 1933-2010 and undated RL.10082
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Unpublished Writings Series, 1933-2009 and undated, 26 boxes
  - Marx
    - Marxian Transformation Problem, 1985 (Box 136)
    - Mill and Marx variants of the canonical classical model, 1982 (Box 136)
    - On Marx, undated (Box 136)
    - Optimality for rational planning of non-Marxian prices that include profit, 1972 (Box 136)
    - The Transformation Problem for rates of return, 1978 (Box 136)
    - Upshot of Marx's Transformation Problem: A candid self-dialogue, 1981 (1 of 2) (Box 136)
    - Upshot of Marx's Transformation Problem: A candid self-dialogue, 1981 (2 of 2) (Box 136)
    - Value, Price, and Profit after a hundred years (on Marx), 1965 (Box 136)
  - Mathematical Economics
    - Abstract for Mathematics of Speculative Price, undated (Box 137)
    - The algebra of matrices (appendix), undated (Box 137)
    - Applied mathematics, 1983 (Box 137)
    - Approximations to roots of matrix and vectors, undated (Box 137)
    - Aspects of complementarity, undated (Box 137)
    - The basic functional identity for an additive metric (associative mean/energy/function/expected utility), 1981 (Box 137)
    - Boulder Dam paradox, undated (Box 137)
    - The calculus of approximate maximization, 1972 (Box 137)
    - Case of independent utilities and partial differential equations, undated (Box 137)
    - Characterization of a general class of means, 1952 (Box 137)
    - Comments on A. Smithies' paper, The Stability of Competitive Equilibrium, 1942-1943 (Box 137)
    - Comments on How deviant can you be?, undated (Box 137)
    - Condensed geometric proof that capital reversal possesses integrated Pareto optimality whenever smooth Clark-Solow technologies sustain non-monopolistic competition, undated (Box 137)
    - Conjugate points in economics, undated (Box 137)
    - Conjugate points in economics, undated (Box 137)
    - Convergence of generalized Newton iterations, undated (Box 137)
    - Converting a many-variation iteration into a powerfully-converging iteration, 1950 (Box 137)
    - Converting a many-variable iteration into a powerfully-converging iteration, undated (Box 137)
    - Cooperation and rivalry between and among classes, undated (Box 137)
    - A crucial third-order partial differential equation for the Expected Utility dogma, 2001 (Box 137)
    - Differential corrections in anti-aircraft trajectories, 1940s (Box 137)
    - Dualisms in economics and in linear programming, 1950 (Box 137)
    - Dynamic programming and functional equations in variational problems, 1953 (Box 137)
    - The equivalence of Newton and Newmann: Iterations in solving matrix and integral equations, 1956 (Box 137)
    - An exact model of betting equilibrium, 1986 (Box 137)
    - The exact order of convergence of an accelerated iteration, 1952 (Box 137)
    - Explanation as strategic description: I. Galileo's free fall without Newton's calculus, undated (Box 137)
    - Form of solutions, undated (Box 137)
    - The Fundamental relation between digital and ordinary linear programming, 1962 (Box 137)
    - A Generalized Laplacian transform for difference equations, undated (Box 137)
    - Global quasi-concavity of indifference contours when 1 good globally violates diminishing marginal utility that is independent, 1975 (Box 137)
    - Hamilton's canonical equations for discrete-time variational systems, 1970s (Box 137)
    - Hamiltonian-Jacobian partial differential equations, undated (Box 137)
    - Harmoniously reconciling post-1890 neo-classical differentiable-continuum mathematical economics with finite discrete mathematics..., undated (Box 137)
    - Hawkins-Simon requirement that what a good requires of itself, directly and indirectly, be less than unity, 1983 (Box 137)
    - Heuristics, undated (Box 137)
    - Interpolation, undated (Box 137)
    - Interrelations between linear programming and game theory, 1951 (Box 137)
    - The law of conservation of energy in classical mechanics, undated (Box 137)
    - The law of conservation of the capital-output ratio, undated (Box 137)
    - The Le Chatelier Principle in linear programming, 1949 (Box 137)
    - Leontief, Hicks, and Keynesian matrices, 1949 (Box 137)
    - Linear programming problem in the calculus of variations, undated (Box 137)
    - Linear programming and economic theory, undated (Box 138)
    - Mathematics of Adam Smith's economy, 1976 (Box 138)
    - Maximum likelihood model, undated (Box 138)
    - Method of continuous substitution, undated (Box 138)
    - Minimization, teleology, and causality in the calculus of variations and in mechanics, undated (Box 138)
    - Minimum laws without teleology in causal dynamic systems, 1963 (Box 138)
    - New measure of complimentary based on inverse demand function and independent of numeric choice, 1982 (Box 138)
    - Notes connected with log normality, 1974 (Box 138)
    - Notes on linear dynamical systems, undated (Box 138)
    - Notes on the dynamic approach to saddlepoints and extremum points, undated (Box 138)
    - Numerical solution of linear equations, undated (Box 138)
    - On almost homogeneous functions, 1959 (Box 138)
    - On an attempted disproof of the "Turnpike Theorem," re: J.R. Hicks, 1960 (Box 138)
    - On the Brownian motion, undated (Box 138)
    - On the correspondence principle, undated (Box 138)
    - On Von Neumann, 1986 (Box 138)
    - One way to construct an "exact index number" for a given homothetic preference field, 1979 (Box 138)
    - Optimal computation of constants in linear differential equations by classical methods, undated (Box 138)
    - Optimality of profit-including prices under ideal planning, undated (Box 138)
    - Part II. Efficiency in continuous flow models, undated (Box 138)
    - Problems in defining universal formulas, 1986 (Box 138)
    - Proof of local dynamic stability in a multiclass growth model (with H. Nagatani), 1976 (Box 138)
    - A proof of the convergence of the method of successive approximation in the solution of normal equations, 1940s (Box 138)
    - Properties of regular means and of Bernoulli means, 1952 (Box 138)
    - Pseudo-maximization and cross elasticities related dualities and elasticities of substitution, undated (Box 138)
    - Reducing a linear programming problem to a non-symmetric game, 1952-1953 (Box 138)
    - The Remarkable Non-Substitution Theorem for systems without primary factors, 1987 (Box 138)
    - Some functional equations arising in economics, 1972 (Box 139)
    - Some fundamental theorems in sequential analysis, undated (Box 139)
    - Some questions about inverse aggregation in Leontief systems, 1959 (Box 139)
    - Sraffa-Leontief profit rate as a vectoral marginal productivity, undated (Box 139)
    - Stochastic asymptotically-homogeneous function with maximum large-scale efficiency, undated (Box 139)
    - Structure of a minimum equilibrium system, 1952 (Box 139)
    - A suggestion for a generalized correlation coefficient, undated (Box 139)
    - A theorem about 2-sided means, 1965 (Box 139)
    - Two conservation laws in theoretical economics, 1970 (Box 139)
    - An unsymmetric way to solve a game or a linear programming problem, undated (Box 139)
    - Variations on capital/output conservation laws, 1982 (Box 139)
    - Weitzman's example of conservative oscillation along an infinite time optimal program pollution, undated (Box 139)
  - Population and Gender
    - Analysis of non-linear demographic models, 1970s (Box 140)
    - Biological fitness and the sex ratio, 1977 (Box 140)
    - A case where natural selection works toward unfitness, intransitivity, and an unbalanced sex ratio, 1977 (Box 140)
    - Classical ecology, 1976 (Box 140)
    - Defining canonical or homogeneous-demis mating processes, undated (Box 140)
    - Discrete-time selection models for sex ratios, 1977 (Box 140)
    - Does female mortality compensate for excess male birth?, 1975 (Box 140)
    - Dogma of equal sex ratios as biologically fit, undated (Box 140)
    - An economic model of evolution, 1971 (Box 140)
    - An economist's non-linear model of self-generated fertility waves, 1975 (Box 140)
    - Equilibrium sex ratio as a maximizing solution, 1980s (Box 140)
    - Ergodic probability distributions in stochastic demographic models, 1980 (Box 140)
    - Exorcising, 1991 (Box 140)
    - The First Complete Economic Model: Variations on Ricardian themes and historical appendix, 1973-1975 (Box 140)
    - Fisher-type selection sans paradox, ambiguity, or hyperbole, 1992 (Box 140)
    - Fisher's Fundamental Theorem on Natural Selection assayed, 1979 (Box 140)
    - Fitness of balanced and unbalanced sex ratios: exact analysis of selection in some nonlinear models, 1977 (Box 140)
    - A fundamental function in population analysis, circa 1938 (Box 140)
    - Gender balance of births in 3-sex models, 1986 (Box 140)
    - General K-allele diploid model I, 1978 (Box 140)
    - General variational theory of Volterra equations occurring in biology and economics, undated (Box 140)
    - Genetic fitness and the sex ratio: natural selection in nonlinear models of population research, 1977 (Box 140)
    - The Hardy-Who Law of Genetics?, 1971 (Box 140)
    - How to produce a multiple root of the Lotka Population Equation, 1975 (Box 141)
    - Intrinsic growth rate and ergodic state for stochastic population systems (Lotka), 1973 (Box 141)
    - Lotka and the Theory of Population Growth, 1942-1943 (Box 141)
    - Lotka model, undated (Box 141)
    - A minimal model of exponential natural increase with non-linear marriage functions, undated (Box 141)
    - Natural selection, 1990s (Box 141)
    - The neutral stability of Mendelian genetics, undated (Box 141)
    - Notes on stability analysis, 1978 (Box 141)
    - On fitness and sex ratios, 1979 (Box 141)
    - On population, 1977 (Box 141)
    - On natural selection, 1983 (Box 141)
    - Paradox of possible permanent hysteresis for age distribution in nonlinear demographic systems, 1978 (Box 141)
    - Personal notes on "Analysis...Population," undated (Box 141)
    - Populations, 1985 (Box 141)
    - Population analysis: individuals rather than genes as players in the struggle for existence: survival value of altruism toward like-gene persons, 1983 (Box 141)
    - Population and economics, 1993 (Box 141)
    - Population theory, 1981 (Box 141)
    - Quasi-limit cycles in age-phased predator-prey population systems, 1976 (Box 141)
    - R Selection and K selection: steady environments, 1982 (Box 141)
    - Revolution in population outlook, undated (Box 141)
    - Second Volterra Paper: The economics of ecology: conservative versus damped biological systems, 1962 (Box 142)
    - Selection for sex balance by biological weight not numbers, 1985 (Box 142)
    - The Serendipity Theorem for optimum population growth in a general lifecycle model, 1974 (Box 142)
    - Singularity conditions for a dynamic system to admit of a surrogate system with fewer degrees of freedom--selfish individuals or selfish genes?, 1983 (Box 142)
    - Some economic biology, 1977 (Box 142)
    - Stabilities of the sex ratio, undated (Box 142)
    - Symmetry deduction of balanced sex ratio of births, 1985 (Box 142)
    - Urn models for random mating, etc., 1977 (Box 142)
    - Uses and ambiguities of fitnesses, 1977 (Box 142)
  - Public Economics
    - A benefit tax model, 1959 (Box 142)
    - A chapter in the history of optimal-feasible taxation on goods and services of Ramsey type, 1971 (Box 142)
    - Consumption tax or income tax in overlapping generations models, 1983 (Box 142)
    - A contribution to the Pure Theory of Public Finance: Lump-sum, consumption, income, and wealth taxation; Loan finance and war, undated (Box 142)
    - Discrete-variable integrability and reciprocity conditions for path-independent line sums: the earned-income tax caper, 1981 (Box 142)
    - The expansionary effects of a balanced budget--notes on the genesis of the theorem, 1940s (Box 142)
    - Government expenditures and the deficit, 1940s (Box 142)
    - Group preference and ideal transfer taxation, undated (Box 142)
    - Income distribution as a public good: a general formulation, 1973 (Box 142)
    - In half loaf: deadweight social loss from incomplete enclosure of common land, 1982 (Box 142)
    - More on public goods and bads: a Road Case, 1959 (Box 142)
    - Notes on deadweight loss due to taxation, undated (Box 142)
    - Notes on the theory of excise taxation, undated (Box 143)
    - Optimal income-tax progression with appropriate deadweight loss, 1976 (Box 143)
    - Public good theory, undated (Box 143)
    - Public good theory: Optimal, feasible pricing of rail, bridge, and road, 1964 (Box 143)
    - Public goods 20 years later, 1974 (Box 143)
    - The Pure theory of public expenditure, undated (Box 143)
    - Pure theory of public finance: A summary, 1972 and undated, 2 folders (Box 143)
    - Ramsey and the theory of optimal taxation, 1960s (Box 143)
    - Response to critiques of his 1954-1955 papers on "The Pure Theory of Public Expenditure," undated (Box 143)
    - Some difficult problems in defining public goods, undated (Box 143)
    - The State as our intergenerational trustee: a case against actuarially-funded pensions, 1988 (Box 143)
    - Survey of fiscal policy, undated (Box 143)
    - Theory of optimal taxation, undated (Box 143)
    - The Theory of taxation, 1968 (Box 143)
  - David Ricardo
    - The First Complete Economic Model: Variations on Ricardian themes and historical appendix, 1973-1975, 2-3 of 3 folders (Box 143)
    - How a bounty on corn affects the Smith-Ricardo (Subsistence-Wage) Model, 1983 Aug (Box 143)
    - Legends: Wellington and Napoleon at Waterloo; Speculators Ricardo, Malthus, and Rothschild ex ante and ex post (Box 143)
    - A master function formulation of canonical Ricardo-Mill comparative advantage, undated (Box 143)
    - A modern treatment of the Ricardian Economy: III. How fixed capital fit into correct and complete competitive theories of distributive shares of wages, profits, and land rents, 2005 (Box 143)
    - Ricardian excesses, then and now, 1986 Jan. (Box 143)
    - David Ricardo, undated (Box 143)
    - David Ricardo, 1990s (Box 143)
    - Ricardo math, 1987 (Box 143)
    - Ricardo on inventions, 1976 (Box 143)
    - Ricardo's endgame, 1995 (Box 143)
    - Ricardo's lost model, 1983 (Box 144)
    - Ricardo's missing 1815 simplest model of distribution: a further critique of Sraffa's uncompleted critique of modern theory, undated (Box 144)
    - Ricardo's missing 1815 simplest model of distribution: a further critique of Sraffa's uncompleted critique of modern theory, 2002 (Box 144)
    - Ricardo's Paradigm on Wage-Reducing Machinery as a Rorschak Ink Blot, 1980 (Box 144)
    - Two-country Ricardian analysis for discrete goos and for a continuum of goods, 1976-1977 (Box 144)
    - Two more Ricardian boners, 1986 Jan. (Box 144)
    - Why Torrens-Ricardo best names comparative advantage, undated (Box 144)
  - Piero Sraffa
    - Bits and pieces on Sraffa, 2005-2006 (Box 144)
    - Concluding the Sraffian system, 2005 (Box 144)
    - Explicating two possible misconceptions relevant to Sraffa's intended critique of marginalism, undated (Box 144)
    - How discrete Sraffa-Samuelson marginalism can closely clone Cobb-Douglas, undated (Box 144)
    - Leontief-Sraffa system, undated (Box 144)
    - Mathematics of Sraffa's joint production, 1984 (Box 144)
    - Notebooks: Sraffa, 3-sex genetics, 1986 (Box 144)
    - An offering for Piero Sraffa, 1898-1983, 1984 (Box 144)
    - On Sraffian values, 1985 (Box 144)
    - Optimality of equal-profit-rate pricing (Sraffa), undated (Box 144)
    - Post-Sraffa non-spurious marginalisms that ape qualitatively J.B. Clark marginal productivities, 2006 (Box 144)
    - Proof that without constant returns to scale Sraffian matrices lose economic relevance, 2004 (Box 144)
    - Six tests (Sraffian), 2005 (Box 144)
    - Piero Sraffa, 1990s (Box 144)
    - Sraffa, undated (Box 144)
    - Piero Sraffa, undated (Box 144)
    - Sraffa economics, 1985 (Box 144)
    - Sraffa's returns and post-Ricardian analysis, 1971 (Box 145)
    - Sraffa-Samuelson marginalism in the multi-primary-factor case: a fourth exploration, undated (Box 145)
    - A strange case of Piero Von Crusoe, 2007 (Box 145)
  - Stochastic Theory, Probability, and Expected Utility
    - Antecedents of Gaussian distribution, 1970s (Box 145)
    - Balanced stochastic growth: Brownian jitter as the natural generalization of deterministic equilibrium, 1980 (Box 145)
    - A basic partial differential equation to test non-introspectively the Expected (Utility) hypothesis, 2001 (Box 145)
    - Black magic: Alchemy of stochastic quality into deterministic quantity, 1980 (Box 145)
    - Brief history of statistics and probability, 1960s (Box 145)
    - Calculating any-odds certainty equivalents in terms of chaos dynamics of even-odds equivalents, 1983 (Box 145)
    - A crucial third-order partial differential equation for the Expected (Utility) dogma, 2001 (Box 145)
    - A flaw in mean-variance methodology, undated (Box 145)
    - Fundamental possibility and impossibility theorems in index number theory, undated (Box 145)
    - How Gauss got too much credit for the normal probability distribution, 1984 (Box 145)
    - How Laws of Large Numbers do reduce risk for diversification within a time period, undated (Box 145)
    - Interdependent stochastic behavior of spot prices, undated (Box 145)
    - Long-run risk tolerance in a fundamentalist model of equities, 1988 (Box 145)
    - No stochastic bricks from non-stochastic straw, 1986 (Box 145)
    - Papers on stochastics, 1996 (Box 145)
    - A rational case at last for more risk tolerance at longer investment horizons?, 1994-1995 (Box 146)
    - Refutations of a long-run stochastic dominance property for Maximizing Expected Utility, 2001 (Box 146)
    - Stochastic comparative statics, 1985 (Box 146)
    - Stochastic Laplacian choice sans cardinal utility and calculus: Associative Means: in Micro and Thermo, 2008 (Box 146)
    - Stochastic pattern of ideal speculative price taking account of storage (Box 146)
    - Stochastic theory, 1990s (Box 146)
    - Stochastic theory, 1981 (Box 146)
    - The surrogate probability function: A possible defense, and extension, for mean-variance approximations, undated (Box 146)
    - Time diversification is costly: A reaffirmation, 1990 (Box 146)
    - Time symmetry and asymmetry in population and general dynamic systems: II. Stochastic, probabilistic models, 1982 (Box 146)
    - Time symmetry and irreversibility: The stochastic case, 1982 (Box 146)
    - Untitled (mean-variance methods), 1997 (Box 146)
    - Untitled (stochastic essay), undated (Box 146)
    - When volatility becomes benign, 2000 (Box 146)
    - When volatility can be benign: measuring by how much and for whom most benign, 1998 (Box 146)
    - Why departing from Expected Utility dogma doesn't leave you open to being made book against, 1988 (Box 146)
  - Thermodynamics
    - Absolute temperature differences and conserved-energy simply defined, undated (Box 146)
    - Axioms for thermodynamic equilibrium in terms of observable isotherms and adiabatics (Box 146)
    - Classical thermodynamical equilibrium system, undated (Box 146)
    - A conservable empirical temperature: The part of thermodynamics that can ignore entropy, 1997 (Box 146)
    - Conserved energy from one testable axiom, 1990 (Box 146)
    - Foundations of thermodynamics, undated (Box 146)
    - How isotherms and adiabats must relate thermodynamically, 1994 (Box 146)
    - The Le Chatelier Principle of Displaced Equilibrium, undated (Box 147)
    - More noise than signal?, ca. 1995 (Box 147)
    - A new form for the solution of simultaneous equations, undated (Box 147)
    - Notes on thermodynamics, 1990s (Box 147)
    - Papers of thermodynamics, 1996 (Box 147)
    - Properties of regular means and of Bernoulli means, 1952 (Box 147)
    - The Second Law of Thermodynamics as merely regression toward the mean: time symmetry vindicated, 1985 (Box 147)
    - Some errors and their corrections (thermodynamics), undated (Box 147)
    - Some needed formal proofs (thermodynamics), undated (Box 147)
    - Structure of a minimum system, undated (Box 147)
    - Thermodynamics, 1980s (Box 147)
    - Thermodynamics on one axiom (2 folders) (Box 147)
    - Thermodynamics without work or heat, 1981 (Box 147)
    - Thermodynamics without work, heat, or temperature: (Box 148)
      - 1. Identifying surrogate energy functions, 1983 (Box 148)
      - 2. Defining a bi-surrogate energy function from spontaneous passive experiments, 1983 (Box 148)
      - 3. Identifying virtual energy functions, 1983 (Box 148)
      - 4. Canonical entropy, temperature, and energy, 1985 (Box 148)
      - 5. Identifying canonical and conceptional energy functions, 1983 (Box 148)
    - A Verhulst-Gauss Model..., 1992 (Box 148)
    - Von Neumann's problematic conjecture about thermodynamics and economics, 1990 (Box 148)
    - A way to exposit thermodynamics, undated (Box 148)
  - Welfare Economics
    - Affirming the existence of a social welfare function, 1975 (Box 148)
    - All macroeconomic theories of distribution are not equal (Siro Lombardini), 1993 (Box 148)
    - Inconsistent and incomplete theories of distribution, 1963, 1975 (Box 148)
    - Lerner-Friedman-Sen egalitarianism reformulated, 1986 (Box 148)
    - Not "To be or not to be?," but "To be son, or father?," 1988 (Box 148)
    - Notes on Turgot, 1977 (Box 148)
    - Pareto's passes at interpersonal welfare functions, 1982 (Box 148)
    - Right and wrong criticisms of mean-variance analysis, 1981 (Box 149)
    - A theory of income distribution, 1968 (Box 149)
    - When and why mean-variance analysis generically fails, 2000 (Box 149)
  - Uncategorized Unpublished Writings, 1933-2007 and undated
    Folders contain writings whose topics do not fall within the subgroups listed above, although there may be some overlap on broader levels. Arranged in alphabetical order by title.
    - Aberrations of mean-variance analysis: untrue logical bias against long shots, 1986 (Box 149)
    - Abstract: The "Saddlepoint Property" and the structure of dynamic heterogeneous capital-good models, 1971 (Box 149)
    - Achieving competitive determinacy by conversion of a Consuming Economy into an equivalent von Neumann Economy, 1970 (Box 149)
    - Addenda on compact probabilities: Gaussian surrogates in the capital asset pricing model and convergence pathologies, 1975 (Box 149)
    - Answers to written questions, 2005 (Box 149)
    - Anti-Pasinetti Equilibrium in discrete-time Sraffian technologies that is generic and Post-Keynesian, 1988 (Box 149)
    - Appendix II (paper unknown), undated (Box 149)
    - Appendix to capital efficiency problem in continuous case, undated (Box 149)
    - Appendix: axiomatic basis for equilibrium relations in classical thermodynamics, undated (Box 149)
    - Autobiographical pieces, 1993 and undated (also includes typescript of 1933 diary) (Box 149)
    - Biographical pieces, 1965-2005 (Box 149)
    - Brief summary of compensation analysis in ordinary demand, undated (Box 149)
    - Brief summary of the Leontief Input-Output system, 1952 and undated, 2 folders (Box 150)
    - Capital theory, 1990s and undated, 5 folders (Box 150)
    - Causal notions in science generally and in economics, undated (Box 150)
    - Comparative statics and duality for the regulated firm, 1976 (Box 150)
    - A complete capital model involving heterogeneous capital goods, 1956 (Box 150)
    - Constancy of velocity when money earns interest, 1980 (Box 150)
    - Contrasting 1955 Kaldor saving with 1962 Pasinetti saving, undated (Box 150)